Blinken, Donald M.; Papers apap080
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Donald M. Blinken Papers
1969-2003
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap080
5.95 cubic ft.
Donald M. Blinken was chairman of the Board of Trustees of the State University of New York from 1978-1990. These records pertain to his tenure in that position.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives by Donald Blinken via Jane Graham of the SUNY Central Archives in January 1997. An additional 1 cubic foot of material received in September 2003 was arranged and described in January 2005.
Biographical Sketch
Donald M. Blinken was born in New York in 1925. He joined the U.S. Army Air Corps in 1944. In 1948 he graduated magna cum laude in economics from Harvard. After 10 years in the retail business, including two in the United Kingdom with Marks & Spencer, he joined the investment firm of E.M. Warburg Pincus, the largest venture capital firm in the United States. He continued to be associated with Warburg Pincus as a managing partner until taking up government service.
In January 1977, Governor Hugh L. Carey appointed Blinken to the Board of Trustees of the State University of New York and subsequently appointed him chairman in July of 1978. He was re-appointed to that office by Governor Mario M. Cuomo and served until 1990. The State University of New York is the nation's largest institution of higher education. It serves hundreds of thousands of students on more than 60 campuses throughout New York. It awarded Mr. Blinken an honorary degree in 1993.
Donald Blinken was sworn in as Ambassador to the Republic of Hungary by Vice President Al Gore on March 29, 1994 and served until 1997.
In addition to his services in education and government, Ambassador Blinken has dedicated his time and energy to the arts. He was named President of the Mark Rothko Foundation in 1976. Mr. Blinken edited Eliminating the Obstacles Between the Painter and the Observer: The Mark Rothko Foundation, 1976-1986. In recent years, Mr. Blinken has also served as vice- chairman of the New York Philharmonic Symphony Society, as a member of the executive committee of the New York Public Library, as a board member and chairman of the Commentary Publication Committee, as a trustee of the Institute of International Education, as overseer of the Nelson A. Rockefeller Institute of Government, and as a member of the Trustees' Council of the National Gallery of Art.
This information came from The Embassy of the United States of America, Budapest Hungary, Donald M. Blinken U.S. Ambassador to Hungary 1994-1997, http://www.usembassy.hu/blinkenb.htm (accessed 20 March 2003). Also from Series 3, Box 1, Folder 1, Donald Blinken Papers, 1969-1993, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University Libraries, University at Albany, State University of New York.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the activities and concerns of Ambassador Blinken as a board member of the Board of Trustees for the State University of New York (SUNY) in 1976 and subsequently as chairman of the Board from 1978 through 1990. The bulk of the papers consists of correspondence between Blinken and members of the Board, the Chancellor, the campus presidents, and New York State government officials. There are also a number of reports regarding the SUNY system or individual SUNY campuses. Prominent topics of concern were the future of the SUNY system (Independent Commission on the Future of SUNY, 1983-1985), relations with independent colleges and universities in New York (Commission on Independent Colleges and Universities, 1978-1984), upgrading intercollegiate athletic competition (Intercollegiate Athletic Board regarding SUNY Buffalo upgrade to Division II, 1985-1986), SUNY and CUNY relations (1976-1989), and concerns about teaching controversial subjects and academic freedom (Dube controversy at SUNY Stony Brook, 1983-1990). SUNY's financial position in both challenging and stable economic times, SUNY's growth as a state wide educational system, and the changing role of the individual campuses are recurring topics.
Although the collection does contain information regarding SUNY campuses, not all of them are represented in this collection. There is little material regarding curriculum other than a 1982 proposal for a degree in Arts Management. There is also little documentation related to student life or faculty at the SUNY schools. There are no personal papers or papers related to other professional, civic, or government positions Ambassador Blinken has maintained.
Additional material acquired in 2003 contains documents related to the individual SUNY campuses, including campus brochures, statements of inauguration, and correspondence between Blinken and members of the Board, the Chancellor, the campus presidents, and the professors of each campus.
Related materials in the University Archives include: the records of the State University of New York, Board of Trustees (APAP-098); the records of the Office of the President (UA-000); and the records of the Student Association of the State University of New York (SASU) (APAP-046).
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - SUNY Schools, 1976-1990
Series 2 - Correspondence, 1976-1990
Series 3 - Subject Files, 1969-2003
Series 4 - SUNY Publications, 1985-1990
Series 1 and 3 are arranged alphabetically. Series 2 is arranged by subject, then chronologically. Series 4 is arranged chronologically.
State University of New York SUNY, Central Administration; Public Servants; Education; Athletics and Sports; New York (State); Albany (N.Y.); Correspondence; Reporting; Administrative records; Publications; Blinken, Donald M.; State University of New York
- SUNY Schools, 1976-1991; 1; 2.32 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  Blinken maintained a small group of files related to specific SUNY schools. The files are arranged alphabetically by the name of the school. The files in Box 5 were accessioned later and processed separately from Box 1, 2, 3, and 4. The files in Box 5 are also arranged alphabetically by the name of the school. Materials within the files are arranged chronologically. They include reports, correspondence, and news clippings regarding a variety of topics.
  There are some files that contain material regarding a specific event or situation. In 1986 the Board of Trustees voted to lift the ban on athletic grant -in-aid at SUNY Buffalo. This change allowed the athletic department to upgrade to Division II in basketball and football with the possibility of upgrading to Division I in subsequent years. Reports from the Intercollegiate Athletic Board are included. Also included is correspondence among the Board members. There are two folders of community correspondence, these include letters from parents, alumni, and members of the community requesting the Board vote to lift the ban and allow the athletic department to upgrade. There are some, though few, requests that the ban not be lifted.
  The Dube Controversy at SUNY Stony Brook, 1983-1990, concerns Professor Ernest Dube who was accused of teaching that Zionism is equivalent to racism. Materials consist of editorials, news clippings, statements from the Dean and other faculty members, correspondence from government officials and members of the Jewish community, and memorandum from the Faculty Rights and Responsibilities group. The issue raised questions of academic responsibility and academic freedom in the teaching of controversial subjects. The controversy continued for several years and Dube's tenure appeal prompted the involvement of the American Association of University Professors in 1986.
  The controversial Louis Farrakan visited the SUNY Old Westbury campus in April 1985. See Box 2, folder 1.
  - SUNY Buffalo, Upgrading Intercollegiate Athletics, 1985-1986 (Box 1 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 1)
  - SUNY Buffalo, Upgrading Intercollegiate Athletics Community Correspondence, 1986 April (Box 1 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 2)
  - SUNY Buffalo, Upgrading Intercollegiate Athletics Community Correspondence, 1986 April-1986 May (Box 1 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 3)
  - SUNY Old Westbury, 1980 January-1980 August (Box 1 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 4)
  - SUNY Old Westbury, 1980 September-1981 September (Box 1 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 5)
  - SUNY Old Westbury, 1982 January-1983 March (Box 1 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 6)
  - SUNY Old Westbury, 1983 April-1984 March (Box 1 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 7)
  - SUNY Old Westbury, 1984 April-1985 April (Box 2 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 1)
  - SUNY Old Westbury, 1986 June-1991 June (Box 2 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 2)
  - SUNY Plattsburg, 1979-1981 (Box 2 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 3)
  - SUNY Plattsburg, 1982-May 1984 (Box 2 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 4)
  - SUNY Plattsburg, 1984 September-1988 (Box 2 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 5)
  - SUNY Pottsdam, 1980-1983 (Box 2 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 6)
  - SUNY Pottsdam, 1984-1985 (Box 2 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 7)
  - SUNY Pottsdam, 1986-1991 (Box 2 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 8)
  - SUNY Purchase, 1979-1981 (Box 2 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 9)
  - SUNY Purchase, 1982-1983 (Box 2 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 10)
  - SUNY Purchase, 1984-April 1985 (Box 3 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 1)
  - SUNY Purchase, 1985 May-1986 April (Box 3 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 2)
  - SUNY Purchase, 1986 July-1988 (Box 3 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 3)
  - SUNY Purchase, 1989-1991 (Box 3 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 4)
  - SUNY Stony Brook, Dube Controversy, 1983 (Box 3 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 5)
  - SUNY Stony Brook, Dube Controversy, 1984-May 1986 (Box 3 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 6)
  - SUNY Stony Brook, Dube Controversy, 1986 September-1987 (Box 3 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 7)
  - SUNY Stony Brook, Grenada Internship Project, 1984 (Box 3 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 8)
  - SUNY Utica/Rome, 1977-August 1978 (Box 3 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 9)
  - SUNY Utica/Rome, 1978 September-1979 (Box 3 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 10)
  - SUNY Utica/Rome, 1979-1980 (Box 4 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 1)
  - SUNY Utica/Rome, 1981 January-1981 February (Box 4 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 2)
  - SUNY Utica/Rome, 1981 March (Box 4 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 3)
  - SUNY Utica/Rome, 1981 April-1981 May (Box 4 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 4)
  - SUNY Utica/Rome, 1981 June-1982 March (Box 4 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 5)
  - SUNY Utica/Rome, 1982 April-1989 (Box 4 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 6)
  - SUNY Albany, General Office File, 1980-1982 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 1)
  - SUNY Albany, General Office File, 1983-1984 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 2)
  - SUNY Albany, General Office File, 1985-1989 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 3)
  - SUNY Binghamton, General Office File, 1979-1981 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 4)
  - SUNY Binghamton, General Office File, 1982-1984 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 5)
  - SUNY Binghamton, General Office File, 1985-1989 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 6)
  - SUNY Brockport, General Office File, 1976-1989 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 7)
  - SUNY Buffalo, General Office File, 1980-1986 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 8)
  - SUNY Buffalo, General Office File, 1987-1988 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 9)
  - SUNY Buffalo, General Office File, 1989-1991 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 10)
  - SUNY Buffalo Foundation Inc., General Office File, 1980-1986 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 11)
  - SUNY Cortland, General Office File, 1980-1988 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 12)
  - SUNY Empire, General Office File, 1980-1984 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 13)
  - SUNY Empire, General Office File, 1985-1989 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 14)
  - SUNY Fredonia, General Office File, 1980-1988 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 15)
  - SUNY Geneseo, General Office File, 1981-1990 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 16)
  - SUNY New Paltz, General Office File, 1980-1983 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 17)
  - SUNY New Paltz, General Office File, 1984-1989 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 18)
  - SUNY Oneonta, General Office File, 1980-1982 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 19)
  - SUNY Oneonta, General Office File, 1983-1989 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 20)
  - SUNY Oswego, General Office File, 1978-1989 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 21)
  - SUNY Stony Brook, Dube Controversy, 1983-1987 October (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 22)
  - SUNY Stony Brook, Dube Controversy, 1987 November-1990 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 23)
  - SUNY Stony Brook, General Office File, 1987-1989 (Box 5 (1-SUNY Schools), Folder 24)
- Correspondence, 1976-1990; 2; 0.66 cubic ft.
  Arranged by subject, then chronologically.
  The bulk of this series is correspondence between Donald Blinken and the other members of the SUNY Board of Trustees, Chancellor Clifton Wharton Jr., presidents of different SUNY campuses, New York government officials, and parents of students. The main subjects of the correspondence include responses to news articles, appointments or reappointments made to the Board, or SUNY related institutions such as the creation of the Rockefeller Institute of Government, the proposal to award a degree in Arts Management in 1982, and materials from symposiums and meetings related to education and budget concerns. There are also news clippings and some information related to state-wide school systems outside of New York. There are some biographical sketches and resumes of Board members. Correspondence in 1979 includes debate about the site of the Utica/Rome campus. There are memos and correspondence related to lawsuits, though there are no details or legal papers in the series or collection.
  Trustee-NY State Legislative correspondence is between Blinken or other members of the Board and members of the New York State Assembly. The main topics of the correspondence are financial matters, reappointments, and new appointments to the Board.
  Correspondence with individuals including Senator Javits, Senator D'Amato, then Congressman Shumer, Governor Carey, Governor Cuomo, and others is mainly related to SUNY budget and financial matters.
  - Trustee Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence), Folder 1)
  - Trustee Correspondence, 1977-July 1978 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence), Folder 2)
  - Trustee Correspondence, 1978 August-1979 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence), Folder 3)
  - Trustee Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence), Folder 4)
  - Trustee Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence), Folder 5)
  - Trustee Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence), Folder 6)
  - Trustee Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence), Folder 7)
  - Trustee Correspondence, 1985 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence), Folder 8)
  - Trustee Correspondence, 1986 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence), Folder 9)
  - Trustee Correspondence, 1987-1990 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 1)
  - Trustee and New York State Legislative Correspondence, 1979 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 2)
  - Trustee and New York State Legislative Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 3)
  - Trustee and New York State Legislative Correspondence, 1982 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 4)
  - Trustee and New York State Legislative Correspondence, 1983-1985 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 5)
  - Trustee and New York State Legislative Correspondence, 1986-1989 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 6)
  - Carey, Governor Hugh Correspondence, 1982 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 7)
  - Cuomo, Governor Mario M. Correspondence, 1978; 1980; 1983-1986; 1988-1989 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Senator Moynihan, Senator D'Amato, Senator Javits Sheldon S. Goldstein, Congressman Shumer, John J. Mather, 1982-1987 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 9)
  - Department of Education Correspondence, 1980; 1985 (Box 2 (2-Correspondence), Folder 10)
- Subject Files, 1969-2003; 3; 2.64 cubic ft.
  The Subject Files contain material related to SUNY organizations, institutions, personnel, and activities, as well as Board activities and responsibilities. The earliest item in the series is from 1969. There is some material regarding a proposed 1976 SUNY/CUNY merger. Files contain reports and correspondence related to this issue and financial concerns for both SUNY and CUNY. However the bulk of materials begin in 1977. The files include correspondence, reports, memorandum, and news clippings. There are a number of files on Chancellor Clifton Wharton Jr., the Commission on Independent Colleges and Universities (CICU), the Independent Commission on the Future of SUNY, and SUNY/CUNY relations.
  Clifton Wharton Jr., former president of Michigan State University, became SUNY Chancellor in 1977. Early files include evaluations by Board members, biographical information about Mr. and Mrs. Wharton, and information about Wharton's accomplishments as an educator and administrator. After Wharton became Chancellor the files include correspondence between him and Blinken as well as other members of the Board, reports related to the SUNY system and individual campuses, memorandum, and news clippings related to higher education. Chancellor Wharton resigned in 1987 to become Chair and CEO of TIAA-CREF.
  The Commission on Independent Colleges and Universities (CICU) files include correspondence between Blinken and the commission and reports regarding SUNY financial matters.
  The Donald M. Blinken Academic Administration Fellowship was established in 1981. It was first called the Administrative Internship. According to Articulation Among Some Science Based Programs in SUNY Units In Western New York, (Blinken Papers, Series 3, Box 3, Folder 3), the objective of the program was to allow a senior SUNY faculty member to gain experience in administrative matters within the University, to look at some of the problems facing SUNY as a whole rather than only from the perspective of a particular campus, and to gain insight into the operations of SUNY central.[1] Reports were issued annually in the spring. The report's title and author appear in the finding aid.
  The Independent Commission on the Future of SUNY was established in 1983. According to the Proposal for an Independent Commission on the Future of the State University of New York (Blinken Papers, Series 3, Box 4, Folder 6) its purpose was to go beyond faculty, staff, and SUNY officials to evaluate SUNY's role and investigate "how its mandate may be discharged more effectively, efficiently, and with greater benefit to citizens and institutions of the state and nation." Their report issued in January of 1985 recommended that SUNY be established as a "public benefits corporation" in order to be extricated from what the commission found to be overregulation from the state government. The recommendation was denied.
  In 1976 there was discussion about SUNY merging with the City University of New York (CUNY) system. Files contain reports and correspondence related to this issue and financial concerns for both SUNY and CUNY.
  - Blinken, Donald M., 2003 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Boyer, Ernest L., 1978-1987 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Budget, 1988-1989 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Campus Related Foundations, 1984 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Chancellor Clifton Wharton Jr., 1977 July-1977 October (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Chancellor Clifton Wharton Jr., 1977 November-1977 December (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Chancellor Clifton Wharton Jr., 1978 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - Chancellor Clifton Wharton Jr., 1979-1982 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Chancellor Clifton Wharton Jr., 1983-1986 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Chancellor Clifton Wharton Jr., 1987-1992 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Chancellor Clifton Wharton Jr., Speeches and Writings, 1971-June 1978 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Chancellor Clifton Wharton Jr., Speeches and Writings, 1978 September-1979 (Box 1 (3-Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - Chancellor Clifton Wharton Jr., Speeches and Writings, 1980-1986 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Chancellor's Public Higher Education Fund, Inc., 1986 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Chancellor's Public Higher Education Fund, Inc., 1987-1990 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Chancellor Search, 1977 February-1977 April (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Chancellor Search, 1977 April-1977 May (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Chancellor Search, 1977 June (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Chancellor Search, 1977 July-1977 November (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - College Teaching, 1985 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Commission on Independent Colleges and Universities, 1978; 1981 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Commission on Independent Colleges and Universities, 1982 (Box 2 (3-Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Commission on Independent Colleges and Universities, 1983 January (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Commission on Independent Colleges and Universities, 1983 March-1984 (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Donald M. Blinken Academic Administrative Fellowship Articulation Among Some Science Based Programs in SUNY Units in Western New York, Robert Stein, 1981 (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Donald M. Blinken Academic Administrative Fellowship A Study of Academic Placement Processes for High-Risk Students Among Selected Colleges of the State University of New York: With a Review of Related Literature, Dennis Callas, 1982 (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Donald M. Blinken Academic Administrative Fellowship Paths For Excellence: A Study of Honors Programs, Honor Societies, and Academic Distinctions in the State University of New York, Mark A. Anderson, 1983 (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Donald M. Blinken Academic Administrative Fellowship Measuring the Use of Library Materials and Services In the Libraries of the State University of New York, Robert E. Burton, 1984 (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 6-7)
  - Donald M. Blinken Academic Administrative Fellowship, 1985 (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Donald M. Blinken Academic Administrative Fellowship Current Issues in Transfer and Articulation: Impact of General Education Requirements, Joint Admissions And Services for Transfer Students, Marjorie W. Lavin, 1986 (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 9-10)
  - Donald M. Blinken Academic Administrative Fellowship The Invisible Minority: American Indian Students in the State University of New York, William A. Starna, 1988 (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 11-12)
  - Donald M. Blinken Academic Administrative Fellowship SUNY's Opportunity Programs: A Research Agenda for the 1990's, Peter R. Barcher (Box 3 (3-Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - Energy Conservation Symposium, 1980 (Box 4 (3-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Engineering and Technology Proposals, 1983 (Box 4 (3-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Exchange Association of Council Members and College Trustees of SUNY, 1977-1979 (Box 4 (3-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Governor's Symposium on International Trade and Finance, 1978 (Box 4 (3-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Independent Commission on the Future of SUNY, 1983 (Box 4 (3-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Independent Commission on the Future of SUNY, ca. 1984 (Box 4 (3-Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Independent Commission on the Future of SUNY, 1984 January-1984 February (Box 4 (3-Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - Independent Commission on the Future of SUNY, 1984 February-1984 May (Box 4 (3-Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Independent Commission on the Future of SUNY, 1984 June (Box 4 (3-Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Independent Commission on the Future of SUNY, 1984 June (Box 4 (3-Subject Files), Folder 10)